KERI Conference Institute. We're a
nonprofit think tank based here in Utah.
We are probably the primary voice when it
comes to privacy among private groups in
Utah. One of the things that we did was we
actually helped get Chris a job. We were
very heavily involved in getting the
privacy commission created. So you owe us
one. Don't forget that.
So a couple other things that we've done
in the privacy space. A couple of years
ago, we became the first state in the
nation to require a geofence warrant. If
law enforcement want to use geofence, they
got to have a warrant to do it. We did
that. Two years ago, we became the first
state in the nation to put guardrails
around the use of real-time surveillance.
To my knowledge, we're still the only
state that actually has that in statute.
So this is something near and dear. This
is one of our core privacy core principles
as an organization among many different
things. One of the things that I learned a
long time ago was to hire people that are
smarter than you. And this person that
works for me is smarter than me. And so
she wrote this for me. And I'm going to
read what she said before I give my
remarks. So, as you know, countries like
the UK and the EU at large are pushing
hard to create a mandatory surveillance
regime through digital IDs. These are
intended to trace every activity, every
service, all of these things that we've
been learning more and more about. We
supported Senate Bill 260 as a vehicle for
rigorously examining the risks and
potential pitfalls of the digital identity
systems, including a study to probe
whether a truly voluntary and untraceable
option is actually feasible in practice.
As the state prioritizes teen mental
health online through privacy-invasive age
verification, we recognize the intent
behind exploring alternatives like SEDI.
But we have to be straightforward about
it. ID systems, even innovative approaches
like SEDI, amplify government involvement
in identity from static issuance to
dynamic, always-on oversight that could
over time challenge user autonomy as seen
in many international examples. We
appreciate the legislature's commitment
guided by the state's Privacy Advisory
Board to examine these realities through
the study process. We lend our support to
continued research and discussion with a
focus on the high bar of preserving
constitutional protections and individual
freedoms amid these systems inherent
challenges. The most fundamental reason
for our engagement in Senate Bill 260 is
an appreciation for the study's focus in
probing the tensions between digital ID
frameworks and the privacy and autonomy
they seek to preserve in service of Utah's
broader goals of safeguarding individual
liberty. However, there are some things
that we would like to see changed, kind of
like the ACO you said. We want to require
opt-in for all data beyond absolute
minimum proofs, just like they said. I can
see a scenario where you go into an
establishment where you need to show your
ID and all they need is a picture to prove
that you are who you say you are and your
date of birth. And they ask for everything
else because they want to package that off
and sell it to data brokers because it's a
way for them to make money. So, we have to
be able to say, no, you can't do that with
this. You know, we have to say that you
don't need that and you don't you cannot
require that for somebody to use your
service. We want to bar government access
to SEDI data via third-party brokers. This
happens all the time. There was a
presentation in a committee hearing on
Wednesday here in Utah where a
transportation company talked about how
they gathered Bluetooth signals to track
traffic patterns in Salt Lake City over a
period of time to determine where
construction was affecting travelers. And
then right after that, there was another
presentation about population data and how
they were gathering all that. And
Representative Chevrier had some very good
questions that went unanswered in that
committee hearing. And I will say that
those people who were speaking at that,
they weren't really happy with her tone
throughout that. After the hearing, I
heard them talking outside. So that's
something you want to follow up on next
time you talk to them. We also want to
establish a right of action against
government agencies for violations. The
easiest way to hold somebody accountable
is make them accountable. Make sure that
they don't do the bad things. Tell them
they're going to go to jail. Tell them
they're going to lose money. This is
something that I propose whenever cities
try to violate. This is so I used to be a
legislator in Missouri once upon a time.
I'm still recovering from that. one of the
things that we did as a legislature was we
put a cap on the amount of fines and fees
that cities could impose on anyone, on
their citizens. And if they exceeded that,
the state could take action. One of those
cities no longer exists. We
disincorporated them and they got annexed
into surrounding cities. Cities have no
constitutional right to do anything.
There's no government agency that has a
constitutional right to exist. There's a
fallacy about co-equal branches of
government that That doesn't exist. That
was made up by President Nixon a long time
ago because, well, he was weird. The fact
is the legislature is the supreme branch
of government because it's the only one
that can fire members of the other two.
And we have to remember that. And this is
the reason why going through the
legislature for this is so important and
not allowing the agencies to just kind of
do whatever they want. You know, we're
working on a bill this year for privacy
that doesn't allow law enforcement to do
anything with surveillance unless the
legislature has already given the go
-ahead. So there are no free trials, no
demos, no free stuff from the feds. And
then they come back and say, well, sorry,
it's helping us. We're doing stuff. It's
like, no, you can't do that. And it
provides a private right of action,
removes qualified immunity. It makes them
accountable for doing things they're not
supposed to do. We also want to impose
ironclad bans on unwanted federal overlays
and revocation overreach. State-to-state
portability is a goal, but the federal
systems like real ID expansions to co-op
SEDI without consent eroding state
control. The study must recommend explicit
prohibitions on such national integrations
preserving voluntary state cooperation
alongside strict due process requirements
for any endorsement revocation to guard
against escalations of centralized power.
So in a nutshell, we are very much in
favor of the study. It's going to show us
what we can do. It's also going to show us
what's going on that we should be worried
about. But, you know, this is very much
one of those things where we're trying to
shove a camel through an eye of a needle.
And if they can't figure out a way to do
it, we need to slaughter the camel and
burn it to the ground. That's essentially
going to be our stance. This is good until
it's not. And once it's not, we're coming
full guns blazing at you. You know, so
we've shown that we have been effective in
some of our other endeavors in the state.
And I'm hopeful that I hope this works
out. You know, I'm not going to lie. I
hope it works out. out. I got five kids.
My oldest is 16. I worry about what could
happen to them. As a legislator, I've
heard all of the horror stories from my
constituents about my kids doing this. Can
you do something? Can you do something?
You know, if something happened, can you
do something? You know, sometimes
government does need to do something.
Sometimes they don't. But legislators,
having been one of them, often feel like
they have to do something. And sometimes
the best thing they can do is nothing. But
I really do hope this can work out the way
we want to. But if it's not. Somebody has
to be held accountable and we have to be
able to just say it's not going to work.
Remember that other people, other
organizations have different incentives.
And so until they realize that our
constitutional rights are the primary
incentive and nothing else really matters
in the situation, we're not going to be
able to be successful at this. So I'm
hoping that Chris and his team and this
process will lay out all of the pros and
cons. All the things we can do, all the
things we shouldn't do, you know, so it
lets everybody know ahead of time kind of
what we're getting into. Thank you very
much.